Chris Anderson: Elon, hey, welcome back to TED.
크리스 앤더슨: 안녕하세요 엔론, TED에 다시 오신 걸 환영합니다.
It's great to have you here.
모시게 되어서 영광입니다.
Elon Musk: Thanks for having me.
엔론 머스크: 초대해주셔서 감사합니다.
CA: So, in the next half hour or so,
CA: 이제 30분 정도 동안
we're going to spend some time
당신이 그리는 흥미로운 미래를
exploring your vision for what an exciting future might look like,
이야기 하고자 하는데요.
which I guess makes the first question a little ironic:
첫 질문이 좀 아이러닉할 것 같습니다.
Why are you boring?
왜 뚫으시려는 거죠?
EM: Yeah.
EM: 네.
I ask myself that frequently.
제 스스로도 그 질문을 자주 하는 편입니다.
We're trying to dig a hole under LA,
저희는 LA의 지하에 구멍을 내려고 하는데요.
and this is to create the beginning
이는 교통 체증을 완화시키기 위한
of what will hopefully be a 3D network of tunnels
3차원 네트워크의 터널이 될 수도 있는
to alleviate congestion.
시발점을 만들기 위함입니다.
So right now, one of the most soul-destroying things is traffic.
교통 체증은 오늘날 우리의 영혼을 탈탈 터는 문제 중의 하나입니다.
It affects people in every part of the world.
세계 모든 사람들에게 영향을 끼치고 있죠.
It takes away so much of your life.
인생에서 너무도 많은 부분을 가져갑니다.
It's horrible.
아주 끔찍합니다.
It's particularly horrible in LA.
LA 에선 특히 더 끔찍하죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: I think you've brought with you
CA: 이를 보여주는 첫 번째 그림을
the first visualization that's been shown of this.
오늘 가져오신 걸로 알고 있는데요.
Can I show this?
보여드려도 될까요?
EM: Yeah, absolutely. So this is the first time --
EM: 네, 당연하죠. 여러분께 처음 보여드리는 겁니다.
Just to show what we're talking about.
저희가 말하고 있는 게 바로 이런 모습입니다.
So a couple of key things that are important
3차원 터널 네트워크를 만드는 데 있어서
in having a 3D tunnel network.
중요한 것이 몇 가지 있습니다.
First of all, you have to be able
우선, 터널의 출입구를
to integrate the entrance and exit of the tunnel
도시의 교통망과
seamlessly into the fabric of the city.
완벽하게 합칠 수 있어야 합니다.
So by having an elevator,
엘리베이터와
sort of a car skate, that's on an elevator,
그에 달린 자동차용 스케이트 보드 같은 게 있다면
you can integrate the entrance and exits to the tunnel network
두 대의 주차 공간만으로도
just by using two parking spaces.
터널의 출입구를 만들어 낼 수 있습니다.
And then the car gets on a skate.
자동차를 스케이트 보드에 싣는 것이죠.
There's no speed limit here,
일단 제한 속도는 없지만
so we're designing this to be able to operate at 200 kilometers an hour.
저희는 시속 200 km 로 작동하게끔 만들고 있습니다.
CA: How much?
CA: 얼마라고요?
EM: 200 kilometers an hour, or about 130 miles per hour.
EM: 시속 200 km 니까, 시속 130 마일 정도요.
So you should be able to get from, say, Westwood to LAX
예를 들자면, 웨스트우드에서 LA 공항까지는
in six minutes -- five, six minutes.
5-6분 정도 걸릴 겁니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: So possibly, initially done,
CA: 그러면 초기에 만들어진 것은
it's like on a sort of toll road-type basis.
요금을 내는 톨게이트 형태의 도로겠군요.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 그렇습니다.
CA: Which, I guess, alleviates some traffic
CA: 지상 도로의 교통량도
from the surface streets as well.
약간은 줄일 수도 있을 것 같네요.
EM: So, I don't know if people noticed it in the video,
EM: 여러분들이 눈치를 채셨는지는 모르겠지만
but there's no real limit to how many levels of tunnel you can have.
터널 깊이에는 제한이 없습니다.
You can go much further deep than you can go up.
위로 올리는 것보다 훨씬 더 깊이 내려갈 수 있죠.
The deepest mines are much deeper than the tallest buildings are tall,
가장 깊은 광산은 가장 높은 빌딩의 높이보다 훨씬 더 깊습니다.
so you can alleviate any arbitrary level of urban congestion
그렇기 때문에 3차원 터널 네트워크로 그 어떤 형태의 도심 정체를
with a 3D tunnel network.
해결할 수 있습니다.
This is a very important point.
이 점이 핵심입니다.
So a key rebuttal to the tunnels is that if you add one layer of tunnels,
터널에 대한 반론으로는 한 층의 터널을 추가해서
that will simply alleviate congestion, it will get used up,
교통량을 해소하더라도 모두 사용이 되어서
and then you'll be back where you started, back with congestion.
처음의 체증 상태로 돌아갈 수 있다는 겁니다.
But you can go to any arbitrary number of tunnels,
하지만 터널의 갯수와 깊이는
any number of levels.
제한이 없습니다.
CA: But people -- seen traditionally, it's incredibly expensive to dig,
CA: 하지만 이전의 경우를 보면, 땅을 파는 비용은 엄청났습니다.
and that would block this idea.
그 때문에 이런 아이디어가 실현되지 못할 수도 있는데요.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 그렇죠.
Well, they're right.
그 말도 맞습니다.
To give you an example, the LA subway extension,
예를 들어 드리자면, LA 지하철 연장 공사가
which is -- I think it's a two-and-a-half mile extension
2.5마일 정도였는데
that was just completed for two billion dollars.
완공되는데까지 20억 달러가 든 걸로 알고 있습니다.
So it's roughly a billion dollars a mile to do the subway extension in LA.
LA 에서 지하철 연장 공사를 하려면 1마일에 10억 달러 정도가 듭니다.
And this is not the highest utility subway in the world.
그렇다고 세계 최고의 지하철 시설은 또 아니에요.
So yeah, it's quite difficult to dig tunnels normally.
일반적으로 터널을 만든다는 것은 꽤나 어려운 게 맞습니다.
I think we need to have at least a tenfold improvement
저는 터널 1마일을 뚫는 데 있어서
in the cost per mile of tunneling.
생산성을 10배 이상 늘려야한다고 생각합니다.
CA: And how could you achieve that?
CA: 실현 방안은 뭔가요?
EM: Actually, if you just do two things,
EM: 사실 두 가지만 해결할 수 있다면
you can get to approximately an order of magnitude improvement,
굉장한 성과를 이룰 수 있고
and I think you can go beyond that.
그 이상도 가능하다고 봅니다.
So the first thing to do is to cut the tunnel diameter
첫 번째는 터널의 지름을
by a factor of two or more.
절반 이상으로 줄이는 겁니다.
So a single road lane tunnel according to regulations
규정에 따르면, 1차선 터널의 경우에는
has to be 26 feet, maybe 28 feet in diameter
지름이 26-28피트 정도가 되어야 하는데
to allow for crashes and emergency vehicles
사고가 날 경우나, 응급 차량
and sufficient ventilation for combustion engine cars.
연소 기관 차량을 위한 충분한 환기 때문입니다.
But if you shrink that diameter to what we're attempting,
하지만 이 지름을 저희가 원하는
which is 12 feet, which is plenty to get an electric skate through,
절반 크기의 12피트로 줄인다면, 전기 스케이트가 다니기에도 충분하고
you drop the diameter by a factor of two
지름을 절반으로 줄이면
and the cross-sectional area by a factor of four,
단면적은 4분의 1로 줄어들고
and the tunneling cost scales with the cross-sectional area.
터널 공사 비용은 이 단면적에 따라 달라집니다.
So that's roughly a half-order of magnitude improvement right there.
이렇게 한다면 거의 두 배에 달하는 향상이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
Then tunneling machines currently tunnel for half the time, then they stop,
그리고 현재의 굴착 기계는 절반의 시간은 굴착에 쓰고
and then the rest of the time is putting in reinforcements
나머지 절반은 터널 벽을 강화하는 데 사용합니다.
So if you design the machine instead
즉, 굴착과 내벽 강화를
to do continuous tunneling and reinforcing,
한 번에, 지속적으로 할 수 있는 기계를 만든다면
that will give you a factor of two improvement.
두 배의 향상을 이끌어낼 수 있습니다.
Combine that and that's a factor of eight.
이 둘을 합치면 8배의 향상이죠.
Also these machines are far from being at their power or thermal limits,
그리고 이 기계들은 성능을 100% 다 쓰고 있지 못하기에
so you can jack up the power to the machine substantially.
기계의 성능도 상당히 향상시킬 수 있습니다.
I think you can get at least a factor of two,
이를 통해 얻을 수 있는 게 최소 2배
maybe a factor of four or five improvement on top of that.
많게는 4-5배의 향상을 추가로 얻을 수 있을 겁니다.
So I think there's a fairly straightforward series of steps
저는 1마일 당 비용을
to get somewhere in excess of an order of magnitude improvement
10배 이상 향상시킬 수 있는 꽤나 분명한 일련의 방법이
in the cost per mile,
있다고 생각합니다.
and our target actually is --
저희는 게리라고 하는
we've got a pet snail called Gary,
애완용 달팽이가 있는데요.
this is from Gary the snail from "South Park,"
이 이름은 "사우스 파크"
I mean, sorry, "SpongeBob SquarePants."
아니 "네모바지 스펀지밥"에서 따왔습니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
So Gary is capable of --
현재 게리는
currently he's capable of going 14 times faster
터널 굴착 기계보다
than a tunnel-boring machine.
14배 정도 빨리 갈 수 있습니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: You want to beat Gary.
CA: 그래서 게리를 이기시겠다?
EM: We want to beat Gary.
EM: 네, 이기고 싶어요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
He's not a patient little fellow,
아주 끈기가 있지는 않아요.
and that will be victory.
그리고 이기면 큰 승리가 될 겁니다.
Victory is beating the snail.
달팽이를 이기는 게 저희 목표입니다.
CA: But a lot of people imagining, dreaming about future cities,
CA: 하지만 많은 사람들이 미래의 도시를 생각할 때
they imagine that actually the solution is flying cars, drones, etc.
해결책은 하늘을 나는 자동차나, 드론 같은 걸 생각하는데요.
You go aboveground.
지상과 떨어져서 말이죠.
Why isn't that a better solution?
왜 이게 더 나은 해결책이 아닌거죠?
You save all that tunneling cost.
터널을 뚫는 비용도 필요 없는데요.
EM: Right. I'm in favor of flying things.
EM: 저도 날아다니는 것들 참 좋아하는데요.
Obviously, I do rockets, so I like things that fly.
저희 로켓도 만들잖아요. 날아다니는 것들 좋아합니다.
This is not some inherent bias against flying things,
비행 물체에 대해 근본적인 편견이 있는 것은 아니지만,
but there is a challenge with flying cars
비행 자동차에는 어려움이 몇 가지 있습니다.
the wind force generated will be very high.
여기서 나오는 바람이 꽤 세다는 것입니다.
Let's just say that if something's flying over your head,
솔직히 말해서, 뭔가가 여러분의 머리 위를 날아다닌다고 해보세요.
a whole bunch of flying cars going all over the place,
비행 자동차가 여기저기 날아다니면
that is not an anxiety-reducing situation.
절대로 안정을 주는 상황은 아닐 겁니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
You don't think to yourself, "Well, I feel better about today."
이렇게 생각하진 않을 거예요. "오늘 기분이 훨씬 더 좋네."
You're thinking, "Did they service their hubcap,
"휠 캡은 점검했겠지?
or is it going to come off and guillotine me?"
갑자기 날아와서 내 목을 치는 거 아냐?"
Things like that.
아마 이렇게 생각하겠죠.
CA: So you've got this vision
CA: 그래서 미래 도시에 대한
of future cities with these rich, 3D networks of tunnels underneath.
당신의 비전은 지하에 수많은 3차원 터널 네트워크가 있는 것인데요.
Is there a tie-in here with Hyperloop?
혹시 하이퍼루프와 연관이 있나요?
Could you apply these tunnels to use for this Hyperloop idea
몇 년 전에 발표하신 하이퍼루프에
you released a few years ago.
터널을 적용할 수 있을까요?
EM: Yeah, so we've been sort of puttering around
EM: 네, 저희는 하이퍼루프와 관련된 것들에 대해
with the Hyperloop stuff for a while.
꽤 오랫동안 고민해왔습니다.
We built a Hyperloop test track adjacent to SpaceX,
저희는 교통에 혁신적인 아이디어를 장려하기 위해
just for a student competition,
학생 공모전 용으로
to encourage innovative ideas in transport.
스페이스X 옆에 하이퍼루프의 시험용 도로를 만들었습니다.
And it actually ends up being the biggest vacuum chamber in the world
그리고 이는 거대 하드론 충돌기 이후
after the Large Hadron Collider,
부피로는 세계에서 가장 큰
by volume.
진공실입니다.
So it was quite fun to do that, but it was kind of a hobby thing,
꽤나 재미있는 일이긴 했지만, 어디까지나 취미 정도였습니다.
and then we think we might --
그러다가 저희는 이것이 가능할지도 모른다고 생각했고,
so we've built a little pusher car to push the student pods,
그래서 그 학생 프로젝트를 밀어줄 자그마한 동체를 만들었고,
but we're going to try seeing how fast we can make the pusher go
이것이 다른 것을 밀지 않을 때 얼마나 빨리 갈 수 있는지를
if it's not pushing something.
보고자 했습니다.
So we're cautiously optimistic
그래서 저희는 겨우 0.8마일의 길이지만
we'll be able to be faster than the world's fastest bullet train
세계에서 가장 빠른 고속 열차보다도 빨리 갈 수 있다고
even in a .8-mile stretch.
조심스럽게 낙관했습니다.
CA: Whoa. Good brakes.
CA: 우와. 브레이크도 잘 만들었네요.
EM: Yeah, I mean, it's -- yeah.
EM: 네, 맞아요, 그러네요.
It's either going to smash into tiny pieces or go quite fast.
산산조각 나거나, 빨리 가거나 둘 중 하나였을 거에요.
CA: But you can picture, then, a Hyperloop in a tunnel
CA: 하지만 당신은 꽤 긴 거리를 터널 안에서 이동하는
running quite long distances.
하이퍼루프를 그렸던 거네요.
EM: Exactly.
EM: 바로 그겁니다.
And looking at tunneling technology,
굴삭 기술을 살펴 보면
it turns out that in order to make a tunnel,
터널을 만들기 위해서는
you have to --
지하수면을
In order to seal against the water table,
막아야 하고
you've got to typically design a tunnel wall to be good
그러자면 5-6 기압을 버틸 수 있는
to about five or six atmospheres.
외벽을 만들어야만 합니다.
So to go to vacuum is only one atmosphere,
진공이나 그에 가까운 상태는
or near-vacuum.
겨우 1기압에 불과합니다.
So actually, it sort of turns out that automatically,
실제로는 지하수면을 버틸 수 있는 터널을 지으면
if you build a tunnel that is good enough to resist the water table,
자연히 진공 상태로
it is automatically capable of holding vacuum.
만들 수 있다는 것이죠.
CA: Huh.
CA: 그렇군요.
EM: So, yeah.
EM: 네, 그렇습니다.
CA: And so you could actually picture,
CA: 그게 다 그려 지시는군요.
what kind of length tunnel is in Elon's future to running Hyperloop?
그렇다면 당신은 어느 정도 길이로 하이퍼루프를 만들 건가요?
EM: I think there's no real length limit.
EM: 딱히 그런 한계는 없는 것 같아요.
You could dig as much as you want.
원하는 만큼 만들 수 있을 거예요.
I think if you were to do something
만약에 DC 에서 뉴욕으로 가는
like a DC-to-New York Hyperloop,
하이퍼루프를 만든다면
I think you'd probably want to go underground the entire way
아마도 전체를 지하로 만들 것 같아요.
because it's a high-density area.
워낙 복잡한 곳이니까요.
You're going under a lot of buildings and houses,
수많은 빌딩과 주택을 지나가겠죠.
and if you go deep enough,
또 깊이만 충분하다면
you cannot detect the tunnel.
터널을 알아챌 수도 없을 거예요.
Sometimes people think, well, it's going to be pretty annoying
가끔, 자기 집 밑으로 터널이 지나가면
to have a tunnel dug under my house.
굉장히 짜증날 거라고 하는 사람들을 만나거든요.
Like, if that tunnel is dug
만약에 주택 아래로
more than about three or four tunnel diameters beneath your house,
터널 지름 3-4배 정도의 깊이에 터널이 지나간다면
you will not be able to detect it being dug at all.
터널이 거기 있는지조차 모를 거예요.
In fact, if you're able to detect the tunnel being dug,
사실 여러분이 어떤 장치를 쓰던
whatever device you are using,
터널이 있는 것을 찾아낼 수 있다면
you can get a lot of money for that device from the Israeli military,
하마스가 뚫어 놓은 터널을 찾는데 혈안이 된 이스라엘 군이나
who is trying to detect tunnels from Hamas,
마약 터널을 찾으려고 하는
and from the US Customs and Border patrol that try and detect drug tunnels.
미국 국경 수비대로부터 엄청난 돈을 벌 수 있을 겁니다.
So the reality is
즉, 현실적으로
that earth is incredibly good at absorbing vibrations,
땅은 진동을 흡수하는 능력이 뛰어나서
and once the tunnel depth is below a certain level,
터널 깊이가 일정 수준 이상이 되면
it is undetectable.
진동 감지가 불가능합니다.
Maybe if you have a very sensitive seismic instrument,
굉장히 정밀한 지질탐사 도구가 있다면
you might be able to detect it.
찾아낼 수도 있겠지만요.
CA: So you've started a new company to do this
CA: 그래서 이 일을 위해서 심심한(뚫는) 회사 (The Boring Company)를
called The Boring Company.
설립했군요.
Very nice. Very funny.
좋아요, 아주 재밌네요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
EM: What's funny about that?
EM: 뭐가 재밌다는 거죠?
CA: How much of your time is this?
CA: 어느 정도의 시간을 할애하나요?
EM: It's maybe ...
EM: 음, 아마도
two or three percent.
2-3% 정도요.
CA: You've bought a hobby.
CA: 취미네요.
This is what an Elon Musk hobby looks like.
여러분은 엔론 머스크 씨의 취미를 보고 계십니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
EM: I mean, it really is, like --
EM: 뭐 그런 셈이네요.
This is basically interns and people doing it part time.
주로 인턴이나 단시간 일하는 사람들이거든요.
We bought some second-hand machinery.
기계도 중고로 샀고요.
It's kind of puttering along, but it's making good progress, so --
아직은 시험단계이지만 좋은 진전을 보이고 있어요.
CA: So an even bigger part of your time
CA: 그러니까 더 많은 시간은
is being spent on electrifying cars and transport through Tesla.
테슬라에서 충전 자동차 같은 운동 수단을 만드는 데 할애하겠네요.
Is one of the motivations for the tunneling project
혹시 터널 프로젝트의
the realization that actually,
실행 동기 중 하나가
in a world where cars are electric and where they're self-driving,
전기 자동차던 자율 주행 자동차건 간에
there may end up being more cars on the roads
현재보다 훨씬 더 많은 차량이
on any given hour than there are now?
도로에 나오는 것에 때문인가요?
EM: Yeah, exactly.
EM: 네, 바로 그겁니다.
A lot of people think that when you make cars autonomous,
많은 사람들이 자율 주행 차랑이 생기면,
they'll be able to go faster and that will alleviate congestion.
더 빠르게 이동할 수 있고, 따라서 체증도 해소될거라 생각합니다.
And to some degree that will be true,
어느 정도는 맞는 말이지만,
but once you have shared autonomy where it's much cheaper to go by car
자동차를 스스로 몰고 가는 것 보다 훨씬 더 싸게, 한 곳에서 다른 곳으로 이동시켜주는
and you can go point to point,
공용의 자율 기관을 가지게 된다면,
the affordability of going in a car will be better than that of a bus.
버스를 타는 것보다 자가용을 이용하는 것이 더 저렴할 것입니다.
Like, it will cost less than a bus ticket.
예를 들어, 버스 요금보다 더 저렴할 겁니다.
So the amount of driving that will occur will be much greater with shared autonomy,
그러면 공유 이동 수단으로 인해 발생할 운전량은 훨씬 더 커질 것이며,
and actually traffic will get far worse.
교통 체증은 더 심해질 겁니다.
CA: You started Tesla with the goal of persuading the world
CA: 당신은 전기차가 자동차의 미래라고
that electrification was the future of cars,
사람들을 설득하는 목표를 가지고 테슬라를 시작했고,
and a few years ago, people were laughing at you.
몇 년 전만 해도 사람들이 비웃었는데요.
Now, not so much.
지금은 훨씬 더 적어요.
EM: OK.
EM: 네, 맞아요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
I don't know. I don't know.
전 모르겠어요. 잘 모르겠네요.
CA: But isn't it true that pretty much every auto manufacturer
CA: 거의 모든 자동차 회사가
has announced serious electrification plans
단기나 중기로 전기차 생산 계획을
for the short- to medium-term future?
발표하지 않았나요?
EM: Yeah. Yeah.
EM: 네, 그렇습니다.
I think almost every automaker has some electric vehicle program.
제 생각에는 거의 모든 회사가 전기 차량 계획이 있는 것 같아요.
They vary in seriousness.
그 중요도는 다들 다르지만요.
Some are very serious about transitioning entirely to electric,
완전 전기차로 가려는 회사들도 있고
and some are just dabbling in it.
시험단계인 회사들도 있어요.
And some, amazingly, are still pursuing fuel cells,
놀랍게도 아직 (수소) 연료 전지를 추구하는 회사도 있지만,
but I think that won't last much longer.
길게 갈 것 같지는 않아요.
CA: But isn't there a sense, though, Elon,
CA: 그런데요 엔론
where you can now just declare victory and say, you know, "We did it."
"우리가 해냈어."라고 승리를 선언할 수도 있지 않나 싶어요.
Let the world electrify, and you go on and focus on other stuff?
세상은 전기차에 집중하라고 하고, 당신은 다른 걸 할 수 있지 않나요?
EM: Yeah.
EM: 그러네요.
I intend to stay with Tesla as far into the future as I can imagine,
저는 최대한 오랫동안 테슬라에 머물 생각이에요.
and there are a lot of exciting things that we have coming.
그리고 준비 중에 있는 흥미로운 일도 많고요.
Obviously the Model 3 is coming soon.
아시다시피, 모델 3이 출시 예정이고요.
We'll be unveiling the Tesla Semi truck.
테슬라 소형 트럭도 출시 준비 중이죠.
CA: OK, we're going to come to this.
CA: 알겠습니다. 그건 이따 다시 얘기하죠.
So Model 3, it's supposed to be coming in July-ish.
그러니까 모델 3이 7월 쯤 나올 예정이죠?
EM: Yeah, it's looking quite good for starting production in July.
EM: 네, 7월에 생산을 시작할 수 있을 것 같아요.
CA: Wow.
CA: 놀랍네요.
One of the things that people are so excited about
사람들이 가장 기대하는 부분 중 하나가
is the fact that it's got autopilot.
자율 주행 기능인데요.
And you put out this video a while back
이 기능에 대한 영상도
showing what that technology would look like.
예전에 하나 보여줬었죠.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 네.
CA: There's obviously autopilot in Model S right now.
CA: 지금 모델 S 에도 자율 주행 기능이 있는데요.
What are we seeing here?
이 영상은 어떤 거죠?
EM: Yeah, so this is using only cameras and GPS.
EM: 지금 카메라와 GPS 만 사용하고 있는데요.
So there's no LIDAR or radar being used here.
LIDAR 나 레이더는 전혀 사용하지 않고 있어요.
This is just using passive optical, which is essentially what a person uses.
사람과 동일하게 시각만을 활용하는 거죠.
The whole road system is meant to be navigated
전체 도로 체계는 시각, 카메라를 통해
with passive optical, or cameras,
주행 가능해야만 하고
and so once you solve cameras
이를 해결하면
or vision,
자율 주행도
then autonomy is solved.
해결되는 것이죠.
If you don't solve vision, it's not solved.
시야를 해결하지 못하면 해결되지 않은 겁니다.
So that's why our focus is so heavily on having a vision neural net
이러한 이유 때문에 저희가 도로 상태에 아주 효과적인 시각 신경망을
that's very effective for road conditions.
구축하는 데에 중점을 두는 이유입니다.
CA: Right. Many other people are going the LIDAR route.
CA: 대부분은 LIDAR를 채택하는데요.
You want cameras plus radar is most of it.
당신은 카메라와 레이더를 택했고요.
EM: You can absolutely be superhuman with just cameras.
EM: (레이더 없이) 카메라만 가지고도 사람을 능가할 수 있어요.
Like, you can probably do it ten times better than humans would,
사람이 하는 것보다 10배 정도
just cameras.
더 잘 할 수도 있을 거예요.
CA: So the new cars being sold right now have eight cameras in them.
CA: 지금 판매 중인 새로운 자동차는 카메라가 8개에요.
They can't yet do what that showed.
아직까진 방금 보여준 것처럼 하지는 못하는데요.
When will they be able to?
언제 쯤 가능할까요?
EM: I think we're still on track for being able to go cross-country
EM: 올해 말까지 LA에서 뉴욕까지
from LA to New York by the end of the year, fully autonomous.
완전 자율 주행으로 횡단하는 계획에 맞춰서 진행 중이에요.
CA: OK, so by the end of the year, you're saying,
CA: 그러니까 그 말은, 연말까지는
someone's going to sit in a Tesla without touching the steering wheel,
사람이 테슬라에 타서 운전대를 잡지 않고
tap in "New York," off it goes.
"뉴욕"을 찍으면 그리로 간다는 말이네요.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 네, 그렇죠.
CA: Won't ever have to touch the wheel -- by the end of 2017.
CA: 2017년 말에는 운전대를 잡을 필요도 없다는 거죠?
EM: Yeah. Essentially, November or December of this year,
EM: 네, 올해 11월이나 12월에는 캘리포니아의 주차장에서
we should be able to go all the way from a parking lot in California
뉴욕의 주차장까지
to a parking lot in New York,
조향장치에 손을 대지 않고
no controls touched at any point during the entire journey.
갈 수 있을 겁니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: Amazing.
CA: 놀랍네요.
But part of that is possible
일반 도로를 달리는 테슬라가
because you've already got a fleet of Teslas driving all these roads.
이미 있으니까 일부는 가능한 건데요.
You're accumulating a huge amount of data of that national road system.
국도 체계에 대한 방대한 데이터도 쌓고 있겠군요.
EM: Yes, but the thing that will be interesting
EM: 네, 하지만 흥미로운 점은
is that I'm actually fairly confident it will be able to do that route
길을 중간에 바꾼다고 하더라도
even if you change the route dynamically.
그 길을 따라 갈 수 있을 거라고 전 꽤 강하게 확신합니다.
So, it's fairly easy --
이건 굉장히 쉽습니다.
If you say I'm going to be really good at one specific route, that's one thing,
만약 여러분이 특정한 경로에 정말 익숙하다면, 그거도 하나겠지만,
but it should be able to go, really be very good,
한 국가에서 고속도로에 진입했을 때
certainly once you enter a highway,
그 안에서 모든 곳으로
to go anywhere on the highway system
갈 수 있을 정도로 그 도로를
in a given country.
잘 알아야만 합니다.
So it's not sort of limited to LA to New York.
즉, LA 에서 뉴욕에만 국한된 게 아니란 뜻이죠.
We could change it and make it Seattle-Florida,
당일에 실시간으로 시애틀에서 플로리다로
that day, in real time.
바꿀 수도 있습니다.
So you were going from LA to New York.
그래서 LA에서 뉴욕으로 가려고 했다가
Now go from LA to Toronto.
LA 에서 토론토로 바꿀 수도 있는 것이죠.
CA: So leaving aside regulation for a second,
CA: 규제에 관한 것은 차치하고
in terms of the technology alone,
기술적인 측면만 봤을 때
the time when someone will be able to buy one of your cars
누군가가 당신의 차를 사서, 말 그대로 핸들에 손을 대지 않고
and literally just take the hands off the wheel and go to sleep
한숨 자다가, 깼을 때 도착했다고
and wake up and find that they've arrived,
알아차리는 걸 안전하게 하는데까지는
how far away is that, to do that safely?
어느 정도의 시간이 걸릴까요?
EM: I think that's about two years.
EM: 한 2년 정도 걸릴 것 같아요.
So the real trick of it is not how do you make it work
진짜로 어려운 것은, 예를 들어 99.9% 의 확률로
say 99.9 percent of the time,
작동하게 만드는 방법이 아니에요.
because, like, if a car crashes one in a thousand times,
왜냐하면 1000분의 1의 확률로
then you're probably still not going to be comfortable falling asleep.
사고가 난다면, 편하게 잠들 수가 없을 테니까요.
You shouldn't be, certainly.
절대로 잠들면 안 되겠죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
It's never going to be perfect.
절대 완벽해 질 수는 없을 거에요.
No system is going to be perfect,
완벽한 시스템은 있을 수 없어요.
but if you say it's perhaps --
하지만, 만약에
the car is unlikely to crash
100번 또는 1000번을 사는 동안에도
in a hundred lifetimes, or a thousand lifetimes,
겨우 한 번 정도 사고가 난다면
then people are like, OK, wow, if I were to live a thousand lives,
일평생 사고를 겪을 일이
I would still most likely never experience a crash,
거의 없을 거고,
then that's probably OK.
저는 그 정도면 괜찮다고 생각해요.
CA: To sleep.
CA: 자는 것도요.
I guess the big concern of yours is that people may actually
제가 생각하기에 당신의 큰 걱정 중 하나는
get seduced too early to think that this is safe,
사람들이 너무 일찍 이 시스템을 안전하다고 생각하고
and that you'll have some horrible incident happen that puts things back.
끔찍한 사고가 나서 모든 걸 되돌리는 게 아닐까 싶은데요.
EM: Well, I think that the autonomy system is likely to at least mitigate the crash,
EM: 음, 제 생각에는 자율 시스템이 정말 드문 경우를 제외하고는
except in rare circumstances.
그래도 사고를 줄일 거라고 생각해요.
The thing to appreciate about vehicle safety
차량 안전에 대해 평가해야할 것은
is this is probabilistic.
이게 확률적이라는 것입니다.
I mean, there's some chance that any time a human driver gets in a car,
제 말은, 어떤 경우에는 사람이 탑승해서
that they will have an accident that is their fault.
실수로 사고를 낼 수도 있다는 것이죠.
It's never zero.
없을 수는 없습니다.
So really the key threshold for autonomy
자율 주행에 있어서의 기준점은
is how much better does autonomy need to be than a person
이 기능을 신뢰하기 위해서
before you can rely on it?
얼마나 더 사람보다 뛰어나야 하느냐 하는 것이죠.
CA: But once you get literally safe hands-off driving,
CA: 하지만 말 그대로 자율 주행이 가능한 자동차를 갖게 되면
the power to disrupt the whole industry seems massive,
전체 산업에 끼치는 영향이 굉장히 커 보이네요.
because at that point you've spoken of people being able to buy a car,
그 단계에서는 주인을 일터에 데려다주고 나서
drops you off at work, and then you let it go
다른 사람들에게 우버 같은 서비스를 제공해서
and provide a sort of Uber-like service to other people,
돈을 벌어다주고, 이를 통해 자동차를
earn you money,
빌리는 비용을 충당할 정도가 될 수도 있고요.
maybe even cover the cost of your lease of that car,
그렇다면 차량을 무료로 사용할 수도 있다는 것처럼
so you can kind of get a car for free.
말씀하셨으니까요.
Is that really likely?
이게 진짜로 가능할까요?
EM: Yeah. Absolutely this is what will happen.
EM: 네. 결과적으로는 이런 일이 일어날 겁니다.
So there will be a shared autonomy fleet
자율 주행 자동차를 공유할 수 있을 거에요.
where you buy your car
사람들이 자동차를 구매해서
and you can choose to use that car exclusively,
혼자서만 사용할 수도 있고,
you could choose to have it be used only by friends and family,
친구나 가족들하고만 공유하거나
only by other drivers who are rated five star,
아니면 최고 등급을 받은 사람들하고만 나눠 쓸 수도 있고,
you can choose to share it sometimes but not other times.
특정 시간대에만 공유하는 경우도 있을 겁니다.
That's 100 percent what will occur.
이런 일이 벌어질 거라고 100% 확신합니다.
It's just a question of when.
단지 시기의 문제죠.
CA: Wow.
CA: 놀랍네요.
So you mentioned the Semi
반 정도는 가능하다고 말씀하셨고
and I think you're planning to announce this in September,
9월 쯤 발표 예정이신데
but I'm curious whether there's anything you could show us today?
혹시나 오늘 저희한테 보여줄 수 있는 게 있으신가요?
EM: I will show you a teaser shot of the truck.
EM: 트럭의 맛보기 사진을 보여드리도록 하죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
It's alive.
살아 있어요.
CA: OK.
CA: 알겠습니다.
EM: That's definitely a case where we want to be cautious
EM: 자율 주행 기능에 대해
about the autonomy features.
굉장히 신중을 기하고 있는 경우입니다.
Yeah.
네, 그래요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: We can't see that much of it,
CA: 잘 보이지는 않는데
but it doesn't look like just a little friendly neighborhood truck.
쉽게 볼 수 있는 자그마한 트럭은 아닌 것 같네요.
It looks kind of badass.
엄청난 녀석으로 보이는군요.
What sort of semi is this?
어떤 면에서 절반이라는 거죠?
EM: So this is a heavy duty, long-range semitruck.
EM: 이건 중장비, 장거리용 세미트럭입니다.
So it's the highest weight capability
운송 가능 무게는 최상급이고
and with long range.
장거리 운행도 가능합니다.
So essentially it's meant to alleviate the heavy-duty trucking loads.
즉, 중장비 트럭 물류를 해소하기 위해 만들어졌죠.
And this is something which people do not today think is possible.
오늘날의 사람들이 가능하다고 생각하지 않는 것 중 한 분야입니다.
They think the truck doesn't have enough power or it doesn't have enough range,
사람들은 전기 트럭이 힘이나, 운행 거리에서 부족하다고 생각하는데
and then with the Tesla Semi
테슬라 세미로
we want to show that no, an electric truck
저희는 전기 트럭이 실제로 디젤 세미보다
actually can out-torque any diesel semi.
낫다는 걸 보여 드리려고 합니다.
And if you had a tug-of-war competition,
만약 트럭들끼리 줄다리기를 한다면
the Tesla Semi will tug the diesel semi uphill.
테슬라 세미가 디젤 세미를 언덕으로 끌고 올라갈 겁니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: That's pretty cool. And short term, these aren't driverless.
CA: 아주 멋지네요. 단기적으로는 무인이 아니에요.
These are going to be trucks that truck drivers want to drive.
트럭 운전사들이 몰고 싶어하는 트럭이 될 것 같네요.
EM: Yes. So what will be really fun about this
EM: 네, 맞아요. 이 트럭이 흥미로운 점은
is you have a flat torque RPM curve with an electric motor,
전기 모터로는 평평한 RPM 곡선을 보이는 반면에
whereas with a diesel motor or any kind of internal combustion engine car,
디젤 모터 같은 내연 기관 모터는
you've got a torque RPM curve that looks like a hill.
언덕 같이 솟아오른 RPM 곡선을 보이죠.
So this will be a very spry truck.
테슬라 세미는 굉장히 빠른 트럭일 겁니다.
You can drive this around like a sports car.
트럭을 스포츠카처럼 운전할 수 있을 겁니다.
There's no gears. It's, like, single speed.
기어도 없습니다. 단일 속도 같은 거죠.
CA: There's a great movie to be made here somewhere.
CA: 뭔가 대단한 영화가 나올 수 있을 것 같네요.
I don't know what it is and I don't know that it ends well,
어떤 종류일 지, 어떻게 끝날 지는 모르겠지만
but it's a great movie.
위대한 영화가 될 거예요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
EM: It's quite bizarre test-driving.
EM: 시험 운전이 꽤 별나긴 했어요.
When I was driving the test prototype for the first truck.
이 첫 트럭의 프로토타입을 운전했을 때
It's really weird, because you're driving around
굉장히 특이했어요.
and you're just so nimble, and you're in this giant truck.
이렇게 큰 트럭을 운전하는데, 엄청 민첩했었거든요.
CA: Wait, you've already driven a prototype?
CA: 잠깐만요, 이미 프로토타입을 몰아 보셨다고요?
EM: Yeah, I drove it around the parking lot,
EM: 맞아요, 주차장에서 했는데
and I was like, this is crazy.
엄청 재미있었어요.
CA: Wow. This is no vaporware.
CA: 놀랍네요. 가상 제품이 아니군요.
EM: It's just like, driving this giant truck
EM: 이 큰 트럭을 몰면서
and making these mad maneuvers.
말도 안되는 움직임을 보였죠.
CA: This is cool. OK, from a really badass picture
CA: 아주 멋지네요. 자, 그럼 정말 굉장한 사진에서
to a kind of less badass picture.
조금은 덜 굉장한 사진을 보죠.
This is just a cute house from "Desperate Housewives" or something.
"위기의 주부들"인가에서 나오는 귀여운 집 사진인데요.
What on earth is going on here?
이게 갑자기 왜 나온거죠?
EM: Well, this illustrates the picture of the future
EM: 이 사진은 미래가
that I think is how things will evolve.
어떻게 변할 지를 보여주는 사진이에요.
You've got an electric car in the driveway.
진입로에는 전기차가 있고요.
If you look in between the electric car and the house,
전기차와 집 사이를 잘 보시면
there are actually three Powerwalls stacked up against the side of the house,
세 개의 파워월이 벽 옆에 위치해 있고,
and then that house roof is a solar roof.
지붕은 태양발전 지붕입니다.
So that's an actual solar glass roof.
즉, 실제로 태양 유리로 되어있습니다.
CA: OK.
CA: 그렇군요.
EM: That's a picture of a real -- well, admittedly, it's a real fake house.
EM: 이건 실제 사진, 인정하자면, 실제 가짜 주택이죠.
That's a real fake house.
실제이지만 가짜인 주택입니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: So these roof tiles,
CA: 그러니까 지붕에 쓴 타일 중
some of them have in them basically solar power, the ability to --
일부는 태양열 발전이 가능하고요.
EM: Yeah. Solar glass tiles
EM: 맞아요. 태양 유리 타일은
where you can adjust the texture and the color
아주 가는 크기로 질감과 색깔을
to a very fine-grained level,
바꿀 수 있고
and then there's sort of microlouvers in the glass,
미세 루버 창 같은 게 유리에 있어서
such that when you're looking at the roof from street level
땅에서 보면
or close to street level,
뒤에 태양전지가 있건 없건
all the tiles look the same
동일하게 보이게
whether there is a solar cell behind it or not.
만들어 줍니다.
So you have an even color
그래서 지면에서 보면
from the ground level.
모두 색깔이 동일하죠.
If you were to look at it from a helicopter,
만약에 헬리콥터에서 본다면
you would be actually able to look through and see
유리 타일 뒤에 태양전지가
that some of the glass tiles have a solar cell behind them and some do not.
있는지 없는지 궤뚫어 볼 수 있긴 합니다.
You can't tell from street level.
땅에서는 모르지만요.
CA: You put them in the ones that are likely to see a lot of sun,
CA: 태양빛을 가장 많이 받을 것 같은 곳에만 설치하니까
and that makes these roofs super affordable, right?
지붕이 꽤 저렴해지겠네요, 맞나요?
They're not that much more expensive than just tiling the roof.
지붕에 타일을 설치하는 것보다 많이 비싸진 않겠군요.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 그렇습니다.
We're very confident that the cost of the roof
저희는 지붕을 설치하는 비용과
plus the cost of electricity --
전기료의 합이
A solar glass roof will be less than the cost of a normal roof
그러니까 태양 유리 지붕 시공에 드는 돈이
plus the cost of electricity.
일반 지붕 시공 비용과 전기료보다 저렴합니다.
So in other words,
다른 말로 하자면
this will be economically a no-brainer,
설치를 안하면 경제를 모르는 멍청이죠.
we think it will look great,
저희는 이게 보기도 좋고
and it will last --
오래 갈 거라고 생각해요.
We thought about having the warranty be infinity,
보증 기간을 평생으로 정할까 생각도 했었는데,
but then people thought,
그러면 사람들이 제품의 질이
well, that might sound like were just talking rubbish,
안 좋을 거라고 생각할 것 같아요.
but actually this is toughened glass.
하지만 실제로 강화 유리거든요.
Well after the house has collapsed
집이 무너져서
and there's nothing there,
아무것도 남지 않아도
the glass tiles will still be there.
유리 타일은 남아있을 거예요.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: I mean, this is cool.
CA: 굉장하군요.
So you're rolling this out in a couple week's time, I think,
제가 듣기로는 몇 주 뒤에
with four different roofing types.
네 가지 종류로 출시될 거라고 하던데요.
EM: Yeah, we're starting off with two, two initially,
EM: 네, 처음에는 두 종류로 시작하고
and the second two will be introduced early next year.
나머지 둘은 내년에 출시할 예정이에요.
CA: And what's the scale of ambition here?
CA: 당신이 생각하는 규모는 어느 정도인가요?
How many houses do you believe could end up having this type of roofing?
이런 종류의 지붕으로 바꾸는 주택이 몇 채나 있을 것 같아요?
EM: I think eventually
EM: 음, 결국에는 대부분의 주택이
almost all houses will have a solar roof.
태양발전 지붕으로 바뀔 거라고 생각해요.
The thing is to consider the time scale here
여기서 생각해야할 기간은
to be probably on the order
한 40-50년 정도로
of 40 or 50 years.
잡고 있어요.
So on average, a roof is replaced every 20 to 25 years.
평균적으로 지붕은 20-25년에 한 번씩 수리를 하거든요.
But you don't start replacing all roofs immediately.
또 전체를 바로 바꾸지도 않죠.
But eventually, if you say were to fast-forward
하지만 결국에는
to say 15 years from now,
예를 들어, 지금으로부터 15년 뒤에는
it will be unusual to have a roof that does not have solar.
태양발전 지붕이 없는 게 이상하게 될 겁니다.
CA: Is there a mental model thing that people don't get here
CA: 혹시 여기에는 사람들이 이해하지 못하는
that because of the shift in the cost, the economics of solar power,
교체 비용으로 인한 태양 발전의 경제성에 관련된 인식 모형이 있나요?
most houses actually have enough sunlight on their roof
대부분의 주택은 필요한 만큼의 전력을 공급할
pretty much to power all of their needs.
충분한 햇볕을 실제로 받고 있잖아요.
If you could capture the power,
이 전력을 가둘 수 있다면
it could pretty much power all their needs.
필요한 만큼 공급이 될 텐데요.
You could go off-grid, kind of.
말하자면 전력선을 끊어도 되겠죠.
EM: It depends on where you are
EM: 사는 지역이나,
and what the house size is relative to the roof area,
지붕의 면적에 따른 집의 크기에 따라 다르겠지만
but it's a fair statement to say
미국 대부분의 주택의 지붕의 면적은
that most houses in the US have enough roof area
가정에서 필요한 전력을 충분히 공급할 수 있을만한
to power all the needs of the house.
크기라고 할 수 있어요.
CA: So the key to the economics
CA: 그러니까 전기차나, 전기 트럭
of the cars, the Semi, of these houses
그리고 이런 주택의 경제성에 있어서 열쇠는
is the falling price of lithium-ion batteries,
당신이 테슬라에서 크게 도박을 건
which you've made a huge bet on as Tesla.
리튬-이온 전지의 가격 인하겠군요.
In many ways, that's almost the core competency.
여러 방면에서 이게 핵심 자산이겠어요.
And you've decided
그리고 당신은 이 자산을 갖기로 결심했고
that to really, like, own that competency,
여기 보이는 것을 통해
you just have to build the world's largest manufacturing plant
리튬-이온 전지의 공급량을 두 배로 늘려줄 세계에서 가장 큰
to double the world's supply of lithium-ion batteries,
생산 공장을 만들었는데요.
with this guy. What is this?
이건 뭔가요?
EM: Yeah, so that's the Gigafactory,
EM: 이건 현재 진행 중인
progress so far on the Gigafactory.
기가팩토리에요.
Eventually, you can sort of roughly see
모양을 보시면, 얼핏 전체적으로
that there's sort of a diamond shape overall,
다이아몬드처럼 보이는데요,
and when it's fully done, it'll look like a giant diamond,
완성이 되면 거대한 다이아몬드처럼 보일 겁니다.
or that's the idea behind it,
그렇게 만들려고 하고 있고요.
and it's aligned on true north.
진북 방향으로 향하고 있죠.
It's a small detail.
작은 디테일이지만요.
CA: And capable of producing, eventually,
CA: 그리고 최종적으로는
like a hundred gigawatt hours of batteries a year.
매년 100 기가와트 시에 달하는 전지를 생산할 수 있고요.
EM: A hundred gigawatt hours. We think probably more, but yeah.
EM: 100 기가와트 시요. 그 이상을 예상하지만, 맞아요.
CA: And they're actually being produced right now.
CA: 지금 현재도 생산하고 있죠.
EM: They're in production already. CA: You guys put out this video.
EM: 네, 생산에 들어갔어요. CA: 당신들이 이 영상을 내보냈는데요.
I mean, is that speeded up?
혹시 빨리 감은 영상인가요?
EM: That's the slowed down version.
EM: 아뇨 느리게 돌린 버전이에요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: How fast does it actually go?
CA: 실제 속도는 어느 정도인가요?
EM: Well, when it's running at full speed,
EM: 최고 속도일 때에는
you can't actually see the cells without a strobe light.
섬광 전구 없이는 전지가 보이질 않아요.
It's just blur.
잔상만 보일 뿐이죠.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: One of your core ideas, Elon, about what makes an exciting future
CA: 엔론, 재미있는 미래를 만드는 당신의 핵심적인 아이디어 중 하나는
is a future where we no longer feel guilty about energy.
에너지에 대해 죄책감을 느끼지 않는 미래인데요.
How many Gigafactories, if you like, does it take to get us there?
만약 필요하다면, 기가 팩토리가 몇 개나 더 있어야 그게 가능한가요?
EM: It's about a hundred, roughly.
EM: 대략적으로는 100개 정도에요.
It's not 10, it's not a thousand.
10개도, 1000개도 아니고,
Most likely a hundred.
100개 정도면 될 것 같아요.
CA: See, I find this amazing.
CA: 굉장히 놀랍다고 저는 생각하는데요.
You can picture what it would take
당신은 이 막대한 화석 연료로부터
to move the world off this vast fossil fuel thing.
세상을 움직이는데 필요한 것을 알고 계시는군요.
It's like you're building one,
50억 달러,
it costs five billion dollars,
아니면 50-100억 달러를 들여서
or whatever, five to 10 billion dollars.
지금 하나를 만들고 있어요.
Like, it's kind of cool that you can picture that project.
이런 프로젝트를 상상할 수 있다는게 굉장히 멋지네요.
And you're planning to do, at Tesla -- announce another two this year.
그리고 테슬라에서 올해에만 두 개를 더 발표할 예정이고요.
EM: I think we'll announce locations
EM: 연말쯤 2-4개 정도의
for somewhere between two and four Gigafactories later this year.
기가팩토리 설치 위치를 더 발표할 것 같아요.
Yeah, probably four.
4개 정도요.
CA: Whoa.
CA: 와우.
(Applause)
(박수)
No more teasing from you for here?
더 발표하실 예고편 같은 건 없나요?
Like -- where, continent?
도시나, 대륙이라도?
You can say no.
아니라고 하셔도 돼요.
EM: We need to address a global market.
EM: 세계 시장을 겨냥해야만 해요.
CA: OK.
CA: 알겠습니다.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
This is cool.
굉장하군요.
I think we should talk for --
음 이제 말해야할 주제가
Actually, double mark it.
음, 중요 표시를 해놔야겠군요.
I'm going to ask you one question about politics, only one.
정치에 대한 질문을 딱 하나만 할게요.
I'm kind of sick of politics, but I do want to ask you this.
개인적으로는 신물이 나긴 하지만, 이 질문을 꼭 드리고 싶네요.
You're on a body now giving advice to a guy --
당신은 지금 한 사람에게 조언을 하고 있잖아요.
EM: Who?
EM: 누구요?
CA: Who has said he doesn't really believe in climate change,
CA: 왜, 그 기후 변화를 믿지 않는 사람이요.
and there's a lot of people out there who think you shouldn't be doing that.
그리고 당신이 그 일을 하면 안 된다고 하는 사람도 많이 있는데요.
They'd like you to walk away from that.
거기서 나왔으면 하는.
What would you say to them?
그들에게 어떤 말을 해주고 싶나요?
EM: Well, I think that first of all,
EM: 우선 말씀드리고 싶은 것은
I'm just on two advisory councils
저는 방을 돌면서 다른 사람들에게
where the format consists of going around the room
특정 주제에 관한 의견을 묻는 형식으로 이루어진
and asking people's opinion on things,
두 자문회의에 있는데
and so there's like a meeting every month or two.
1-2달 마다 한 번 미팅을 가져요.
That's the sum total of my contribution.
제가 하는 일은 이게 다라고 할 수 있어요.
But I think to the degree that there are people in the room
가끔 회의에서 기후 변화나
who are arguing in favor of doing something about climate change,
사회 문제를 위해
or social issues,
의견을 피력하는 사람들이 있고,
I've used the meetings I've had thus far
저는 이 회의를 이용해서
to argue in favor of immigration and in favor of climate change.
이민이나 기후 변화의 편에 서서 의견을 내왔어요.
(Applause)
(박수)
And if I hadn't done that,
그리고 이건 회의 주제에도 없던 내용이었는데,
that wasn't on the agenda before.
만약 제가 그러지 않았다면,
So maybe nothing will happen, but at least the words were said.
아무 일도 일어나지 않았겠지만, 최소한 그에 대한 언급은 됐겠죠.
CA: OK.
CA: 그렇군요.
(Applause)
(박수)
So let's talk SpaceX and Mars.
이제 스페이스X와 화성에 대해 얘기해보죠.
Last time you were here,
지난번에 여기 오셨을 때,
you spoke about what seemed like a kind of incredibly ambitious dream
재사용이 가능한 로켓을 만들겠다는 어쩌면 말도 안 될 정도로
to develop rockets that were actually reusable.
야망이 가득한 꿈에 대해서 발표를 하셨는데요.
And you've only gone and done it.
실제로 그 일을 해냈어요.
EM: Finally. It took a long time.
EM: 마침내 그랬죠. 꽤 오래 걸렸어요.
CA: Talk us through this. What are we looking at here?
CA: 자세히 좀 말해주세요. 여기 보이는 건 뭐죠?
EM: So this is one of our rocket boosters
EM: 음, 이건 우주 아주 높은 곳에서
coming back from very high and fast in space.
빠른 속도로 떨어지고 있는 로켓 추진체에요.
So just delivered the upper stage
빠른 속도로 상단부를
at high velocity.
막 올렸을 겁니다.
I think this might have been at sort of Mach 7 or so,
상단부를 궤도에 올리려면
delivery of the upper stage.
마하7 정도의 속도가 돼야할 겁니다.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: So that was a sped-up --
CA: 그러니까 이건 빨리감기...
EM: That was the slowed down version.
EM: 아뇨, 느리게 돌린 거에요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: I thought that was the sped-up version.
CA: 저는 또 빨리 감은 버전인 줄 알았네요.
But I mean, that's amazing,
여튼, 놀랍습니다.
and several of these failed
처음 성공할 때까지
before you finally figured out how to do it,
몇 번의 실패가 있었는데,
but now you've done this, what, five or six times?
그래서 지금은 한 대여섯번 정도 성공 하지 않았나요?
EM: We're at eight or nine.
EM: 여덟, 아홉 번 정도 한 것 같네요.
CA: And for the first time,
CA: 그리고 처음으로
you've actually reflown one of the rockets that landed.
돌아온 로켓을 쏘는데 성공했고요.
EM: Yeah, so we landed the rocket booster
EM: 네, 로켓 추진체를 받아서
and then prepped it for flight again and flew it again,
다음 발사를 위해 준비한 뒤 다시 날려 보냈죠.
so it's the first reflight of an orbital booster
재비행과 관련이 있는 곳에 대해서는
where that reflight is relevant.
궤도 추진체 최초의 재비행이에요.
So it's important to appreciate that reusability is only relevant
빠르고 완전한 상태일 때 재사용성이 적절하다는 것을
if it is rapid and complete.
평가하는 것이 중요합니다.
So like an aircraft or a car,
비행기나 자동차는
the reusability is rapid and complete.
재사용성이 빠르고 완벽하죠.
You do not send your aircraft to Boeing in-between flights.
비행 사이에 비행기를 보잉으로 보내지 않습니다.
CA: Right. So this is allowing you to dream of this really ambitious idea
CA: 그렇군요. 이 덕분에 10년, 20년 뒤에
of sending many, many, many people to Mars
수많은 사람들을 화성으로 보내려는
in, what, 10 or 20 years time, I guess.
원대한 꿈을 꿀 수 있게 됐군요.
EM: Yeah.
EM: 그렇습니다.
CA: And you've designed this outrageous rocket to do it.
CA: 그리고 실행하기 위해 이 엄청난 로켓을 만들었고요.
Help us understand the scale of this thing.
크기가 어느 정도인지 저희에게 알려주시겠어요?
EM: Well, visually you can see that's a person.
EM: 네, 보시다시피 저게 사람이에요.
Yeah, and that's the vehicle.
네, 그리고 저건 로켓이고요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: So if that was a skyscraper,
CA: 만약 저게 고층 건물이라면,
that's like, did I read that, a 40-story skyscraper?
40층 짜리라고 읽은 것 같은데 그게 맞나요?
EM: Probably a little more, yeah.
EM: 조금 더 클 것 같은데 비슷하긴 할 겁니다.
The thrust level of this is really --
이 로켓의 추진력은,
This configuration is about four times the thrust of the Saturn V moon rocket.
구성에 따르면 새턴 4호 달 로켓의 4배에 달합니다.
CA: Four times the thrust of the biggest rocket humanity ever created before.
CA: 추진력이 인류가 만든 가장 큰 로켓의 4배라고요.
EM: Yeah. Yeah.
EM: 네, 맞아요.
CA: As one does. EM: Yeah.
CA: 하나가요. EM: 네.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
In units of 747, a 747 is only about a quarter of a million pounds of thrust,
747의 부품에서, 747의 추진력이 25만 파운드니까
so for every 10 million pounds of thrust,
추진력 천만 파운드 당 747기
there's 40 747s.
40대가 되겠네요.
So this would be the thrust equivalent of 120 747s, with all engines blazing.
모든 엔진이 켜지면 747 120대 정도의 추진력이 나옵니다.
CA: And so even with a machine designed to escape Earth's gravity,
CA: 그러니까 지구 중력을 벗어나게끔 만들어진 기계로,
I think you told me last time
지난번에 제게 이 비행체가
this thing could actually take a fully loaded 747,
747 기체와, 사람, 짐, 등등을
people, cargo, everything,
다 궤도에 올릴 수 있다고
into orbit.
하셨는데요.
EM: Exactly. This can take a fully loaded 747 with maximum fuel,
EM: 맞아요. 이 로켓은
maximum passengers, maximum cargo on the 747 --
연료, 승객, 짐을 가득 실은 747을
this can take it as cargo.
짐으로 실을 수 있어요.
CA: So based on this,
CA: 이걸 기반으로,
you presented recently this Interplanetary Transport System
이렇게 생긴 행성간 이동 시스템을
which is visualized this way.
최근에 발표하셨어요.
This is a scene you picture in, what, 30 years time? 20 years time?
이 사진은 당신이 그리는 20년? 30년 뒤의 미래인가요?
People walking into this rocket.
이 로켓에 사람들이 탑승하는 거요.
EM: I'm hopeful it's sort of an eight- to 10-year time frame.
EM: 8-10년 내에 이뤄졌으면 해요.
Aspirationally, that's our target.
열망을 품고 목표로 하고 있어요.
Our internal targets are more aggressive, but I think --
내부 목표는 더 공격적이지만요.
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: OK.
CA: 그렇군요.
EM: While vehicle seems quite large
EM: 비행체가 꽤 커보이고,
and is large by comparison with other rockets,
다른 로켓들에 비해서 크기도 하지만,
I think the future spacecraft
미래의 우주선은
will make this look like a rowboat.
이 로켓마저 보트처럼 보이게 만들 겁니다.
The future spaceships will be truly enormous.
미래의 우주선은 진짜로 거대할 거에요.
CA: Why, Elon?
CA: 왜 그렇죠, 엔론?
Why do we need to build a city on Mars
당신이 하고 싶어하는 일이
with a million people on it in your lifetime,
죽기 전에 화성에 백만명을 보내서
which I think is kind of what you've said you'd love to do?
도시를 건설하는 거라고 알고 있는데, 왜 그래야 하나요?
EM: I think it's important to have
EM: 영감을 주고 끌리는 미래를 꿈꾸는 게
a future that is inspiring and appealing.
중요하다고 생각해요.
I just think there have to be reasons
저는 사람이 아침에 일어나서
that you get up in the morning and you want to live.
살고 싶게 하는 이유가 중요하다고 믿거든요.
Like, why do you want to live?
마치, 왜 살려고 하나요?
What's the point? What inspires you?
목적이 뭐에요? 영감을 주는 것은요?
What do you love about the future?
미래에 대해 꿈꾸는 것은요?
And if we're not out there,
만약 이 우주에 지구 밖에 없다면,
if the future does not include being out there among the stars
미래에 우리가 우주에서,
and being a multiplanet species,
다른 행성에서도 살아가는 종족이 아니라면,
I find that it's incredibly depressing
저는 이러한 미래가 없다는 사실이
if that's not the future that we're going to have.
꽤나 실망럽다고 생각해요.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: People want to position this as an either or,
CA: 사람들은 이걸 그렇게 큰 문제로 취급하진 않아요.
that there are so many desperate things happening on the planet now
기후에서부터 빈곤에 이르기까지
from climate to poverty to, you know, you pick your issue.
많은 긴박한 문제들이 현재에도 벌어지고 있거든요.
And this feels like a distraction.
그래서 이건 약간 논지를 흐리게 만드는 느낌이에요.
You shouldn't be thinking about this.
이러한 미래를 생각할 게 아니라
You should be solving what's here and now.
현재의 문제를 풀어야 한다는 사람들도 있을 거에요.
And to be fair, you've done a fair old bit to actually do that
솔직히 말하자면, 지속가능한 에너지에 있어서
with your work on sustainable energy.
당신은 충분히 큰 역할을 했어요.
But why not just do that?
왜 거기에 머물지 않으려는 거죠?
EM: I think there's --
EM: 음, 제 생각에
I look at the future from the standpoint of probabilities.
저는 미래를 확률의 관점에서 바라보는 것 같아요.
It's like a branching stream of probabilities,
확률들이 가지를 친다고 생각하는데요,
and there are actions that we can take that affect those probabilities
우리가 하는 행동 중에서 이런 확률에 영향을 주는 것도 있고,
or that accelerate one thing or slow down another thing.
하나를 가속시키거나, 느리게 만드는 행동이 있을 거에요.
I may introduce something new to the probability stream.
이런 확률들에 새로운 걸 추가할 수도 있을 거고요.
Sustainable energy will happen no matter what.
지속가능한 에너지는 분명 일어날 일입니다.
If there was no Tesla, if Tesla never existed,
만약 테슬라가 아니거나, 테슬라가 없었더라도
it would have to happen out of necessity.
필요에 의해 생겼을 거에요.
It's tautological.
똑같은 말입니다만,
If you don't have sustainable energy, it means you have unsustainable energy.
지속가능한 에너지가 없다면 지속 불가능한 에너지만 있다는 것이죠.
Eventually you will run out,
언젠가는 다 써버릴 것이고,
and the laws of economics will drive civilization
경제학의 법칙에 따라 사람들은
towards sustainable energy,
피할 수 없이 지속가능한 에너지로
inevitably.
갔을 겁니다.
The fundamental value of a company like Tesla
테슬라와 같은 회사의 근본적인 가치는
is the degree to which it accelerates the advent of sustainable energy,
지속가능한 에너지의 등장을 가속화하는 정도에 있습니다.
faster than it would otherwise occur.
없어도 일어나는 것보다 빠르게요.
So when I think, like,
테슬라 같은 회사에서
what is the fundamental good of a company like Tesla,
근본적인 선의가 뭐냐고 한다면,
I would say, hopefully,
일어나면 좋은 일들을
if it accelerated that by a decade, potentially more than a decade,
10년, 혹은 더 빨리 앞당기는 것이라고
that would be quite a good thing to occur.
대답하고 싶습니다.
That's what I consider to be
테슬라의 근본적이고 열망적인 장점이라고
the fundamental aspirational good of Tesla.
제가 생각하는 부분입니다.
Then there's becoming a multiplanet species and space-faring civilization.
그리고 여러 행성에 살고 우주 여행을 하는 문명입니다.
This is not inevitable.
이건 필수적인 것은 아닙니다.
It's very important to appreciate this is not inevitable.
이게 필수적이지 않다고 인지하는 것이 아주 중요합니다.
The sustainable energy future I think is largely inevitable,
지속가능한 에너지가 있는 미래는 대개 일어날 수 밖에 없는 일이지만,
but being a space-faring civilization is definitely not inevitable.
우주여행을 하는 문명은 꼭 일어날 일은 아니에요.
If you look at the progress in space,
우주에 대한 발전을 살펴보면,
in 1969 you were able to send somebody to the moon.
1969년 우리는 사람을 달에 보낼 수 있었습니다.
1969.
1969년도에요.
Then we had the Space Shuttle.
그리고 스페이스 셔틀이 있었죠.
The Space Shuttle could only take people to low Earth orbit.
스페이스 셔틀은 사람을 오직 저궤도로만 데려갈 수 있었죠.
Then the Space Shuttle retired,
그러다가 스페이스 셔틀이 은퇴했고,
and the United States could take no one to orbit.
미국은 사람을 궤도로 보낼 수 없었습니다.
So that's the trend.
이게 현재 경향이에요.
The trend is like down to nothing.
이제 아무 것도 없어요.
People are mistaken when they think
사람들은 기술이
that technology just automatically improves.
자연히 발전한다고 생각하는데 이건 오산이에요.
It does not automatically improve.
스스로 나아지지 않아요.
It only improves if a lot of people work very hard to make it better,
많은 사람들이 열심히 노력해서 더 낫게 만들어야 발전하지,
and actually it will, I think, by itself degrade, actually.
가만히 나둔다면 실제로는 퇴보한다고 생각해요.
You look at great civilizations like Ancient Egypt,
고대 이집트와 같은 위대한 문명을 보면,
and they were able to make the pyramids,
과거에는 피라미드를 만들 수 있었지만,
and they forgot how to do that.
이제는 만드는 방법을 잊었어요.
And then the Romans, they built these incredible aqueducts.
그리고 로마인들은 놀라운 수로를 만들었지만,
They forgot how to do it.
이제는 까먹었죠.
CA: Elon, it almost seems, listening to you
CA: 엔론, 당신의 말을 듣고,
and looking at the different things you've done,
당신이 한 일들을 보고 있자면
that you've got this unique double motivation on everything
모든 것들에 대해 독특한 두 가지 동기부여가 있는 것 같아
that I find so interesting.
굉장히 흥미롭네요.
One is this desire to work for humanity's long-term good.
하나는 인류의 장기 선을 위해 일하는 것이고,
The other is the desire to do something exciting.
다른 하나는 재미있는 일을 하려는 욕구 같아요.
And often it feels like you feel like you need the one to drive the other.
가끔 보면 당신은 목표로 도달하게끔 만드는 어떤 것을 이용하는 것 같아요.
With Tesla, you want to have sustainable energy,
테슬라에서는 지속가능한 에너지를 만들고자 해서,
so you made these super sexy, exciting cars to do it.
아주 잘 빠지고 멋있는 자동차를 이용했어요.
Solar energy, we need to get there,
태양열 발전을 위해서는
so we need to make these beautiful roofs.
아름다운 지붕을 만들었어요.
We haven't even spoken about your newest thing,
아직 당신의 최신 결과물에 대해서는 얘기도 나누지 않았고,
which we don't have time to do,
시간도 없긴 한데,
but you want to save humanity from bad AI,
당신은 나쁜 인공지능으로부터 인류를 구하고 싶어서,
and so you're going to create this really cool brain-machine interface
사람들에게 무한한 기억과 텔레파시와 같은 것을 주기 위해
to give us all infinite memory and telepathy and so forth.
아주 멋진 뇌-기계 인터페이스를 만들려고 하죠.
And on Mars, it feels like what you're saying is,
그리고 화성에는, 당신의 말을 들으면 마치,
yeah, we need to save humanity
우리는 인류도 구하고,
and have a backup plan,
백업 플랜도 있어야 하는데다가,
but also we need to inspire humanity,
그들에게 영감을 줘야만해요.
and this is a way to inspire.
그리고 이게 그 방법인 것 같아요.
EM: I think the value of beauty and inspiration
EM: 아름다움과 영감의 가치는
is very much underrated,
아주 저평가 되어 있다고 생각해요.
no question.
질문의 여지가 없이요.
But I want to be clear.
하지만 한 가지 확실히 하고 싶은게 있어요.
I'm not trying to be anyone's savior.
저는 누군가의 구세주가 되고 싶은게 아니에요.
That is not the --
저는 미래에 대해 생각하되
I'm just trying to think about the future
슬퍼지지 않고자
and not be sad.
하는 거에요.
(Applause)
(박수)
CA: Beautiful statement.
CA: 아름다운 말이네요.
I think everyone here would agree
저는 여기 계신 모든 분들이
that it is not --
동의할 거라고 생각해요.
None of this is going to happen inevitably.
이것들 중 무조건 일어날 일은 없다는 것을요.
The fact that in your mind, you dream this stuff,
한 가지 사실은, 당신은 이런 것을 꿈꾸고,
you dream stuff that no one else would dare dream,
다른 누군가는 감히 생각도 못한 것을 꿈꾸고,
or no one else would be capable of dreaming
또는 다른 사람은 당신만큼 복잡하게 생각할 수도 없는
at the level of complexity that you do.
꿈을 꾼다는 것 같아요.
The fact that you do that, Elon Musk, is a really remarkable thing.
엔론 머스크, 당신이 이런 일을 한다는 건 굉장하다고 생각해요.
Thank you for helping us all to dream a bit bigger.
우리 모두 더 큰 꿈을 꿀 수 있게 도와줘서 감사해요.
EM: But you'll tell me if it ever starts getting genuinely insane, right?
EM: 그런데 만약 시작된다면 좀 미쳤다고 말씀하실 거죠?
(Laughter)
(웃음)
CA: Thank you, Elon Musk. That was really, really fantastic.
CA: 감사합니다, 엔론 머스크. 아주 환상적이었어요.
That was really fantastic.
정말 환상적이었습니다.
(Applause)
(박수)